<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hornbyes hornbook Iudge not too rashly, till through all you looke; if nothing then doth please you, burne the booke. By William Hornbye, gent.</title>
            <author>Hornby, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118882</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854089</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854089</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03687)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 963:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hornbyes hornbook Iudge not too rashly, till through all you looke; if nothing then doth please you, burne the booke. By William Hornbye, gent.</title>
                  <author>Hornby, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Aug. Math[ewes] for Thomas Bayly, and are to be sold at his shop in the middle row neere Staple Inn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴ (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hornbooks --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:1"/>
            <p>HORNBYES HORNBOOK.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Iudge not too raſhly, till through all you looke;</l>
               <l>If nothing then doth pleaſe you, burne the Booke.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of master and student</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>By <hi>William Hornbye,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Aug. Math.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Bayly,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in the middle Rowneere Staple Inn. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE AND HOPEFVLL YOVNG Gentleman, Sir ROBERT CARR, Barronet,</hi> W. H. wiſheth increaſe of all <hi>honorable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY honeſt, humble, harmleſſe horning-book,</l>
               <l>From whence young Schollers their firſt learning tool</l>
               <l>To you I dedicate (true generous ſpirit)</l>
               <l>Your early towardneſſe, and vertues merit</l>
               <l>A farre more worthy worke, then here I can</l>
               <l>Set out, that ne're was Accademian:</l>
               <l>Yet in my homely verſe (perhaps) you'l find</l>
               <l>Something, a little which may pleaſe your mind.</l>
               <l>My booke's but Harden to ſome Holland wit,</l>
               <l>And ſo with home-ſpun plaineſt beſt doth fit;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:3"/>
               <l>For in a plaine and honeſt ſimple ſtile,</l>
               <l>There lurkes no craft, no ſubtiltie, nor guile.</l>
               <l>Here is no vaine, nor yet prophane diſcourſe,</l>
               <l>To make you by the reading be the worſe;</l>
               <l>I would not ſtaine your thoughts with ſuch a booke,</l>
               <l>Nor haue your chaſte eyes on ſuch follies looke.</l>
               <l>This in a manner doth but plainely ſhow</l>
               <l>How Schollers doe begin, and how they grow</l>
               <l>To <hi>Learning</hi> by their industrie and paine,</l>
               <l>That rich inestimable Iem to gaine.</l>
               <l>(The <hi>Horn-book</hi> is at first Arts Nurce, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence</l>
               <l>We ſuck the milke of our intellîgence)</l>
               <l>We must be perfect in our letters all,</l>
               <l>E're we to ſpelling, and to reading fall.</l>
               <l>By this Originall, we win (indeed)</l>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> glory, if we ſo proceede:</l>
               <l>And as this booke (ſweet Sir) but young appeares</l>
               <l>So tis reſpondent vnto youthfull yeares,</l>
               <l>Fit for your young dayes and minoritie,</l>
               <l>Vntill you come to ſenioritie.</l>
               <l>Into my mind this cogitation came,</l>
               <l>Vnto your ſelfe to dedicate the ſame,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Preſuming of your fauour, and your loue,</l>
               <l>That what I write your vertues will approue</l>
               <l>Vpon your face, although your yeares be greene,</l>
               <l>The portrature of modeſtie is ſeene.</l>
               <l>Though in the Teenes you ſcarce haue enterd yet,</l>
               <l>You haue a manly Carriage, pregnant Wit.</l>
               <l>God be your good guide, and your happy ſpeede</l>
               <l>Euen as you haue begun, ſo to proceede</l>
               <l>In honourable vertues worthy <hi>Car,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To make your name ſhine like the Morning-Star.</l>
               <l>Thus Honourable Sir, I take my leaue,</l>
               <l>In hope you kindly will (this mite) receiue.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all humble ſeruice, <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL YOVNG GEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TLEMAN, THOMAS GRANTHAM, Eſquire, Sonne and Heire to Sir THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS GRANTHAM, Knight; <hi>W.H. wiſheth all Health and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>BEtwixt two Roſes, I a Lilly place,</l>
               <l>Three flowers moſt ſweet, and louely flouriſhing,</l>
               <l>All hopefull, by Gods bleſsing and his grace,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Vertues Garden</hi> ſweetly vp to ſpring;</l>
               <l>A true and worthy Gardiner they haue</l>
               <l>From choaking weedes, them to preſerue and ſaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God was aſsiſtant to ſo wiſe Elector,</l>
               <l>When firſt he choſe ſo ſure a friend indeed</l>
               <l>To be his childrens Gardian and Protector,</l>
               <l>Who with an honourable care, and heed,</l>
               <l>Kindly reſpects his deare poſteritie,</l>
               <l>Which ſure ſhall lift his honour to the skie.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>To you ſole Sonne vnto this worthy Knight,</l>
               <l>I likewiſe dedicate my ſimple <hi>Muſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Conioyning you together, as tis right,</l>
               <l>Becauſe a Simpathie in loue you vſe:</l>
               <l>As you are Fellowes both at Schoole and play,</l>
               <l>(I hope) I blameleſſe ioyne you partners may.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thus relying on your kind affection,</l>
               <l>That courteouſly you will this booke receiue,</l>
               <l>I boldly ſhroud it vnder your protection:</l>
               <l>And here in briefe I humbly take my leaue,</l>
               <l>Wiſhing your vertues to grow more and more</l>
               <l>In multitudes, like Sand vpon the ſhore.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moſt officious and obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quius in what he can, <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous young Gentleman, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Rocheſter Carre: W.H.</hi> wiſheth increaſe of all <hi>ſpirituall and temporall bleſſings.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>RIght (generous Sir) I kindly you intreate</l>
               <l>To be Copartner, for to patronize</l>
               <l>This little Orphant of my braines conceite,</l>
               <l>Which to you alſo in all humble wiſe</l>
               <l>I dedicate; my <hi>Muſe</hi> ſhall ſtill ingage her</l>
               <l>As well vnto the <hi>Minor</hi> as the <hi>Maior.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And thus my loue in equall ballance peaſde</l>
               <l>I equallize your worths with equall thought,</l>
               <l>My onely wiſhes are, you would be pleaſde,</l>
               <l>Kindly to take what my poore wit hath wrought,</l>
               <l>Your kind acceptance is my chiefeſt gaines,</l>
               <l>I wiſh no greater gurdeon for my paines.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>At your ſeruice to be commanded,</hi> W. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY <hi>Braine</hi> now (gentle Reader)'s brought to bed</l>
               <l>Of that a while ſhe painefull laboured:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ypen a carefull Mid-wiues part hath plaid</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſee her of her Orphant ſafely layd,</l>
               <l>Wrap'd vp in raggs of meane intelligence,</l>
               <l>Without the Robes of learned eloquence:</l>
               <l>And though ſhe be ſhees not abortiue borne,</l>
               <l>Though Retorique her ſhaps did ne're adorne:</l>
               <l>Nor is ſhe of a baſe and baſtard ſtraine,</l>
               <l>Her Parentage is honeſt, ſimple, plaine,</l>
               <l>All of her Father, true <hi>Inuentions</hi> getting,</l>
               <l>As tis moſt honeſt, requiſite and fitting.</l>
               <l>She is no filtch-line of anothers wit,</l>
               <l>Such Theft ſhe hateth and abhorreth it,</l>
               <l>And ſhe dare looke euen with a modeſt grace,</l>
               <l>Her better <hi>Muſe</hi> with boldneſſe in the face.</l>
               <l>A Cottyers child may be as truly got,</l>
               <l>As is a Courtyers euery way, why not?</l>
               <l>As faire and louely too in ſhape and face,</l>
               <l>And euen as well adorn'd with inward grace,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:7"/>
               <l>And proue as faithfull, iuſt, and plaine a man,</l>
               <l>For he nere temporiſe, nor flutter can;</l>
               <l>He doth not know the art of Adulation,</l>
               <l>He neuer is acquainted with ſuch faſhion,</l>
               <l>The difference of theſe two in this appears,</l>
               <l>Th'one Robes of ſilke, th'otherraggs doth weare:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo although (this homely brat of mine)</l>
               <l>Doth want rich robes of Art to make it ſhine</l>
               <l>Through out all places, where it haplie goes,</l>
               <l>Yet meere ſimplicitie, and truth it ſhowes.</l>
               <l>The two collauded, and applauded ſprings,</l>
               <l>Where all the <hi>Muſes</hi> moſt delitious ſings,</l>
               <l>Within their armes did neuer me infold,</l>
               <l>Nor did my eyes their glory yet behold;</l>
               <l>Such bliſſe to me (alas) did ne're belong,</l>
               <l>I had the greater iniurie and wrong.</l>
               <l>Then (gentle Reader) if that title faire,</l>
               <l>With thy good nature I may right compare:</l>
               <l>Pardon my Muſe, which for no ill intent,</l>
               <l>Into the world I homely here haue ſent.</l>
               <l>Here is no enuy that at all doth lurke</l>
               <l>In this my harmeleſſe Muſes little worke:</l>
               <l>And if that any diſcontent doth grow,</l>
               <l>Tis not my fault, but theirs which take it ſo.</l>
               <l>Thoſe people then whoſe conſciences are cleare</l>
               <l>From all ſuch things as I haue written here,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:7"/>
               <l>Accept my minds true meaning and good will,</l>
               <l>More then my Retorique, my Art and skill;</l>
               <l>If ſome cannot commend it nor defend it,</l>
               <l>Then in their wiſdomes let them kindly mend it:</l>
               <l>If neither; ceaſe then a malignant tongue,</l>
               <l>And doe a harmleſſe honeſt Muſe no wrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, as you like him, <hi>Cornu-apes.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19496:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>HORNBYES HORNBOOK.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe <hi>Horn-booke</hi> of all books I doe commend,</l>
               <l>For the worlds knowledge, it doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</l>
               <l>There is no book vnder heauens copious cope,</l>
               <l>Of mightie volume, large and full of ſcope,</l>
               <l>Compoſde of the pure quintiſſence of wit,</l>
               <l>But ſure the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> full containeth it.</l>
               <l>What euer can be written, read, or ſaid,</l>
               <l>Are firſt of letters fram'd, compoſde, and made;</l>
               <l>Each word, and ſentence are in order ſet,</l>
               <l>Deriued from the Engliſh <hi>Alphabet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of all chiefe learning, litrature and Art,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Horn-booke</hi> is the ground, which doth impart</l>
               <l>A world of Science; and great Art and skill</l>
               <l>Comes from the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> be it good, or ill;</l>
               <l>And I haue reaſon to colland the ſame,</l>
               <l>Becauſe tis ſounding ſomewhat neere my name.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Rtoritian,</hi> and the great <hi>Logition;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Arethmatition,</hi> and the black <hi>Magition;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:9"/>
               <l>The learn'd <hi>Phiſitian,</hi> and the quaint <hi>Muſitian;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The grounded <hi>Grecian,</hi> and the ſound <hi>Hebritian,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which mount <hi>Parnaſſus</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erſity.</hi>
                  </note> Hill; and not to ſeeke</l>
               <l>In <hi>Engliſh, Latin, Hebrew,</hi> and in <hi>Greeke.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And all that deeply politick are found,</l>
               <l>Had firſt their knowledge from the <hi>Horn-bookes</hi> ground<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Great learned Preachers of Diuinitie,</l>
               <l>Which with the heauens haue neare affinitie;</l>
               <l>Profound ſound Doctors of the <hi>Morrall</hi> Law,</l>
               <l>Firſt from the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> did their reaſon draw.</l>
               <l>And from <hi>Chriſts</hi> Cradle, to his bloody Croſſe,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Chriſt-croſſe-row</hi> is Character'd each loſſe,</l>
               <l>And great affliction that to man doth fall;</l>
               <l>Being taught by <hi>Patience</hi> how to beare withall.</l>
               <l>There's an old ſaying to be vnderſtood,</l>
               <l>And yet (in deed) is not ſo old, as good:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In my beginning God be my good ſpeed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In grace and vertue that I may proceed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>vertue</hi> is the <hi>Alpha</hi> of Gods <hi>grace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How we ſhould run th'<hi>Omega</hi> of our race.</l>
               <l>And what is <hi>Patience</hi> but a <hi>vertue</hi> pure,</l>
               <l>Which to the end all Croſſes doth endure:</l>
               <l>He that hath <hi>Patience,</hi> is a perfect man,</l>
               <l>And well is skild the <hi>Chriſt-croſſe-row</hi> to skan:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Patience</hi> is euen the ground, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence proceeds</l>
               <l>All goods conceits, and charitable deeds.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And <hi>charitie</hi> is euen the firme foundation,</l>
               <l>On which a man doth found his ſoules ſaluation.</l>
               <l>Then to conclude, theſe <hi>vertues</hi> firſt doe flow</l>
               <l>From the <hi>Originall,</hi> the <hi>Chriſt-croſſe-row.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The little Infant that receiues his birth,</l>
               <l>To paſſe his <hi>pilgrimage</hi> vpon the earth,</l>
               <l>Takes firſt a reſpite, and a time to grow,</l>
               <l>Before he comes vnto the <hi>Chriſt-croſſe-row;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And at his <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> euen from the <hi>Font,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Receiues the Croſſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> vpon his front,</l>
               <l>In ſigne that he ſhould neuer ſhame, nor feare,</l>
               <l>The Croſſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> life to beare.</l>
               <l>For three or fower yeares ſpace, like to a lamb,</l>
               <l>He ſpends his time in ſporting, and in gam:</l>
               <l>His wanton courage ſomewhat then to Coole,</l>
               <l>His Parents puts him to a petty Schoole.</l>
               <l>Then after that, he takes a pritty pride,</l>
               <l>To weare the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> dangling by his ſide:</l>
               <l>And was it not well arm'd with plate and horne,</l>
               <l>T'was in great danger to be rent and torne:</l>
               <l>For in his ſport, ſometimes he falleth out</l>
               <l>With his Schoole-fellow, ſo they haue a bout</l>
               <l>At Buff, and counter-buff; the <hi>Horr-bookes</hi> then</l>
               <l>Are all the weapons for theſe ſtout tall men;</l>
               <l>As tis agreeing with their childiſh yeares,</l>
               <l>They briefely fall together by the eares</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:10"/>
               <l>For a ſmall cauſe, their quarrell doth begin,</l>
               <l>Euen for a Point, a Counter, or a Pin,</l>
               <l>And as a trifle ſmall their friendſhip brake;</l>
               <l>Euen ſo a toy, them friends againe doe make:</l>
               <l>For they (good Lads) in mallice cannot ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Within their breſts they anger neuer keepe;</l>
               <l>So to their ſports they freſh againe doe fall,</l>
               <l>As if they had not fallen out at all:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The good nature and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>For he to learne yet, cannot well betake him,</l>
               <l>But finding toyes, &amp; ſports, ſits down to lake him</l>
               <l>With Top, and Top-ſtick, and his Eldern-guns,</l>
               <l>And neuer thinks of time, how faſt it runs;</l>
               <l>And thus with ſuch like lakings, childiſh play,</l>
               <l>He many times doth paſſe the time away,</l>
               <l>Vntill his Tutor with an awfull hand,</l>
               <l>Not ſternely tho but with a mild command,</l>
               <l>Makes him affect his booke, not with a twig,</l>
               <l>But with a Nut, an Almond, or a Fig.</l>
               <l>And hauing ſo the childs affection won</l>
               <l>(He ſaith) ſweet Lad come, and thy <hi>Horn-book</hi> con.</l>
               <l>And ſo the <hi>A.B.C.</hi> he firſt is taught;</l>
               <l>From that to ſpelling, he is after brought;</l>
               <l>And being right inſtructed for to ſpell,</l>
               <l>He learn's his <hi>Sillables</hi> and <hi>Vowels</hi> well.</l>
               <l>Then with due teaching he doth well conſider</l>
               <l>By's Maſters rule how he may put together.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>The <hi>Horn-booke</hi> hauing at his ſingers end,</l>
               <l>Vnto the <hi>Primer</hi> he doth next aſcend;</l>
               <l>When his capacitie, againe doth alter</l>
               <l>From that, he goes into the holy <hi>Pſalter;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then next to that, into the Booke of Bookes</l>
               <l>The ſacred <hi>Bible</hi> modeſtly he lookes;</l>
               <l>As in a glaſſe, where he may plainely ſee</l>
               <l>Both what he is, and what he ought to bee.</l>
               <l>How that he was conceiu'd-and borne in ſin,</l>
               <l>Since his firſt breath to draw, he did begin:</l>
               <l>There he may ſee that he's a mortall man,</l>
               <l>Subiect to ſin, and hard reſiſt it can;</l>
               <l>There is a ſoueraigne ſalue moſt gratious ſent</l>
               <l>To heale ſick ſoules which truly doe repent;</l>
               <l>There he may ſee, that ſin originall</l>
               <l>Came firſt from <hi>Eue</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> by their fall;</l>
               <l>Before the <hi>Maſculine</hi> I here prefer</l>
               <l>The <hi>Feminine,</hi> becauſe ſhe firſt diderr:</l>
               <l>The woman with inticements did begin</l>
               <l>To draw old Father <hi>Adam</hi> vnto ſin;</l>
               <l>And ſince her firſt diſeaſe, it ſtill infects</l>
               <l>Vnto this day a number of her ſects.</l>
               <l>There he may ſee by the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> fall,</l>
               <l>A ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> did redeeme vs all</l>
               <l>With bis moſt deareſt blood, ſhed on the Croſſe,</l>
               <l>The greateſt gratious bleſsing that e're was.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:11"/>
               <l>And as the Prouerbe old doth teach vs, ſo</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We firſt muſt creepe, before we well can goe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So from the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> we muſt firſt incline,</l>
               <l>Before we can attaine to things diuine.</l>
               <l>Diuine or humaine, or in what degree</l>
               <l>Of Art and knowledge, what ſo e're it be;</l>
               <l>And as the <hi>Bible</hi> is the well of preaching,</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> is the ground of teaching;</l>
               <l>Yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not hold my argument ſo ſtrong,</l>
               <l>To doe the <hi>Accidence</hi> one iot of wrong.</l>
               <l>A ſecond worthy ground there is in truth</l>
               <l>Of learning, apter for more able Youth:</l>
               <l>But yet he cannot vnto this attaine,</l>
               <l>Before the <hi>Horn booke</hi> doth direct him plaine;</l>
               <l>By skill, good will, and times experience,</l>
               <l>He enters ſtraight into the <hi>Accedence:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There's the true ground <hi>Gramarians</hi> ground vpon,</l>
               <l>To clime vnto the Hill of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hellicon:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To that, they'r brought with charge &amp; large expences,</l>
               <l>To know their <hi>Monds,</hi> their <hi>Caſes,</hi> &amp; their <hi>Tences:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By that th'ar learn'd to ſcan and proue a <hi>Verſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And alſo how to Conſter, and to Perſe;</l>
               <l>Then with the <hi>Latin Abcee</hi> they begin,</l>
               <l>And ſo from ſtep to ſtep, more skill doe win:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Puriles</hi> next is vſde in Schollers making,</l>
               <l>In which Youth gather profit by paines taking.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>By viewing <hi>Cato,</hi> there they may rehearſe</l>
               <l>For good examples, many a golden verſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ouids</hi> laſciuious booke, in's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt to loue,</l>
               <l>Is good to reade, but not ſo good to proue.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tully</hi> for eloquence doth beare the bell,</l>
               <l>For a ſweet ſtile, he doth the reſt excell.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corderus</hi> Dyalogues doth true relate</l>
               <l>Good preſidents for youth to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mitate.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Terence</hi> a worthy booke, and ready meanes</l>
               <l>Timboulden boyes, by acting of his <hi>Sceanes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Ouids Metamorphoſis</hi> is had</l>
               <l>Diuers examples, that are good and bad:</l>
               <l>There <hi>Phaeton</hi> through pride did get a fall,</l>
               <l>A goodly preſident for pride to all;</l>
               <l>For he beyond his skill, needs would aſſay,</l>
               <l>That which turn'd quickly to his owne decay.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Acteon,</hi> for his longing, and his luſt</l>
               <l>After chaſt <hi>Dyna,</hi> was transformed iuſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Narciſſus</hi> that proud ſelfe-conceited Elſe,</l>
               <l>Louing his ſhadow, fondly loſt himſelfe.</l>
               <l>There may they find <hi>Diana's</hi> dignitie,</l>
               <l>For ſimple pureneſſe, and pure chaſtetie:</l>
               <l>With diuers more examples I could write,</l>
               <l>But time will not permit me to recite.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virgell,</hi> a booke that doth exceed the reſt;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Horace,</hi> equallized with the beſt.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:12"/>
               <l>By theſe good meanes, and Gods aſsiſting grace,</l>
               <l>They run the happy <hi>Helliconian</hi> race;</l>
               <l>If God preſerue their labours, and their health,</l>
               <l>They proue good members in a Common-wealth</l>
               <l>As Muſterd-ſeed of all the ſeeds that be,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Simile.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Is the leaſt graine: but yet by proofe we ſee,</l>
               <l>The flittering foules of heauen may liue &amp; breed</l>
               <l>In thoſe large branches that from it doe ſpread;</l>
               <l>And though it be (indeed) a graine but ſmall,</l>
               <l>Yet doth it beare a ſound round price withall.</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> is the ſeede and graine</l>
               <l>Of skill, by which we learning firſt obtaine:</l>
               <l>And though it be accompted ſmall of many,</l>
               <l>And haply bought for two pence, or a penny,</l>
               <l>Yet will the teaching ſomewhat coſtly be,</l>
               <l>Ere they attaine vnto the full degree</l>
               <l>Of Schollerſhip and Art: for at a word,</l>
               <l>It firſt doth hatch the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erſitie chollers</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Helliconian</hi> bird,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Learning;</hi> a pretious Iem I doe account,</l>
               <l>Which doth all treaſure in the world ſurmount;</l>
               <l>It is a bleſsing, if it well be vſde,</l>
               <l>But to a curſe it turns, if ill abuſde;</l>
               <l>Learning's a Ladder, grounded vpon faith,</l>
               <l>By which we clime to heauen (the Scripture ſaith.</l>
               <l>And tis a meanes to hurrie men to hell,</l>
               <l>If grace be wanting for to vſe it well:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>So the <hi>Horn-book</hi> without Gods grace-guiding ſtill</l>
               <l>May be an introduction vnto ill;</l>
               <l>To euery one God doth a Talent giue,</l>
               <l>To trie how they can proſper, thriue and liue.</l>
               <l>That profitable ſeruant that hath fower,</l>
               <l>If frugall, ſhall haue thrice as many more;</l>
               <l>He that hath three, his labour ſhall not ceaſe;</l>
               <l>For to inrich him with a great increaſe.</l>
               <l>He that hath two, with diligence and paine,</l>
               <l>Shall be requited with a double gaine;</l>
               <l>And that ſame ſloathfull ſluggard that hath one,</l>
               <l>If fruitleſſe buried, ſhall be ſure of none.</l>
               <l>And now my <hi>Horn-booke</hi> I may rightly apply</l>
               <l>Both to the <hi>Clergie,</hi> and the <hi>Laetie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How many <hi>Paſtors</hi> are there,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Careles and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards.</hi>
                  </note> that ſhould feede</l>
               <l>Their flocke (alas) yet ſtarue them in their need</l>
               <l>Which doe that worthy function much neglect</l>
               <l>For worldly cauſes, or ſome by reſpect,</l>
               <l>Who the regardles hirelings part doe play</l>
               <l>That care not how their ſheepe doe goe aſtray,</l>
               <l>But leaue them all at random, here and there,</l>
               <l>For greedy Wolues to ſpoyle, deuower, &amp; teare;</l>
               <l>Theſe ill deſerue (I ſay) in ſuch a caſe,</l>
               <l>Their liuings, learning, and ſo worthy place:</l>
               <l>Theſe are blind guids, blind in their inward ſight,</l>
               <l>Which grope at Noone-tide, with a Candle light.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:13"/>
               <l>(Me thinks) neglect of this their ſacred function</l>
               <l>Should ſtrike with horror, a moſt ſharp co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>punctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>Into their Marble hearts: for there's a woe</l>
               <l>Pronounc'd gainſt thoſe, which ſlip their duty ſo;</l>
               <l>Who more reſpect the world, and worldly pelfe,</l>
               <l>Then for to profit others, or himſelfe</l>
               <l>In ſoules ſaluation; ſuch deſire to gaine</l>
               <l>The riches of this world, which are but vaine:</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Iſops</hi> Cock, which of more worth did deeme</l>
               <l>A Barly-corne, then Iem of of great eſteeme.</l>
               <l>Theſe kind of ſcatter-graces right are found</l>
               <l>Like him that hid his Talent in the ground:</l>
               <l>For ſuch as theſe I mourne, &amp; make great mone,</l>
               <l>They better neuer had the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> knowne.</l>
               <l>Yet many a <hi>Citie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and carefull Paſtors.</hi>
                  </note> many a <hi>Towne</hi> is bleſt</l>
               <l>Here in our Land, with <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the beſt,</l>
               <l>Who take moſt earneſt paines, and honeſt heed,</l>
               <l>Not for to fleece their flocks, but them to feede,</l>
               <l>And with a ſpeciall care, and conſcience cauſe,</l>
               <l>Reforme the wicked to religious lawes:</l>
               <l>So they which ſit in <hi>Ignorance</hi> black night,</l>
               <l>They doe inlighten with their ſplendent light.</l>
               <l>Theſe are true <hi>Shepheards,</hi> euen to <hi>Chriſts</hi> deſire,</l>
               <l>And hee'l reward them with a <hi>Heauenly</hi> hire:</l>
               <l>Bleſſed are they, that euer they did know</l>
               <l>The <hi>Horn-booke,</hi> and the happy <hi>Chriſt-croſſe-row.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>The great graue worthy Iudges of the Land,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſt Judges</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>That doe with care and conſcience vnderſtand</l>
               <l>The poore mens cauſes, be they right or wrong,</l>
               <l>To giue the right, where right doth true belong,</l>
               <l>(I hope) will with my <hi>Horn-booke</hi> free diſpence,</l>
               <l>Knowing that knowledge is deriu'd from thence.</l>
               <l>Before we learne, we learne to know each letter,</l>
               <l>Or elſe to learne to reade, is nere the better.</l>
               <l>And to all gentle Iuſtices of Peace,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vpright Juſtices.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Who doe their Talents (in their charge) increaſe,</l>
               <l>In doing Iuſtice with a ſingle eie,</l>
               <l>Without reſpect of men, or briberie,</l>
               <l>My <hi>Horn-booke</hi> very humbly I commend,</l>
               <l>Hoping that learning they will ſtill defend.</l>
               <l>To all Schoole-founders,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Schoole-founders</hi>
                  </note> that haue euer been</l>
               <l>Moſt beneficiall vnto Schollers ſeene,</l>
               <l>By Schooles errecting, and protecting thoſe</l>
               <l>Vnder their fauours, which in learning growes</l>
               <l>To full maturitie; theſe doe ſupport</l>
               <l>Poore Schollers in a charitable ſort,</l>
               <l>Theſe happy Stewards haue their Talents ſpent</l>
               <l>Pleaſing to God, and for a good intent:</l>
               <l>To theſe my <hi>Horn-booke</hi> likewiſe I commend,</l>
               <l>Knowing the <hi>Muſes</hi> they doe beſt befrend.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lavvyers and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnies.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>The buſie <hi>Lawyers,</hi> and the briefe <hi>Atturneys,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which euery <hi>Term-time</hi> take moſt tedious iornies</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:14"/>
               <l>To toyle, and moyle, to ride through thick &amp; thin,</l>
               <l>And all to bring their fees more roundly in;</l>
               <l>Whoſe onely labours to this purpoſe tends,</l>
               <l>They would haue all men rathere foes then friends,</l>
               <l>Becauſe by controuerſie they doe gaine,</l>
               <l>And concord makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beggers, they complaine.</l>
               <l>Theſe from the <hi>Horn-book</hi> firſt did draw their skill,</l>
               <l>Good cauſe haue they to beare it great good will.</l>
               <l>A Conſtable's a iudicious man,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>able.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>If he performe his Office wiſely can:</l>
               <l>But if vnlearnedly he doe amiſſe,</l>
               <l>(Ales) the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> was no friend of his.</l>
               <l>The learned <hi>Poet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Poet</hi>
                  </note> that in <hi>Poetrie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth mount aloft vnto the loftie skie</l>
               <l>In high conceits, through diuine inſpiration</l>
               <l>Who for his Art, is held in admiration;</l>
               <l>That which I write, will grant for to be true,</l>
               <l>And giue vnto the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> praiſe due.</l>
               <l>The Third-bare <hi>Poet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Thread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare Poet.</hi>
                  </note> or the Ballad-maker,</l>
               <l>That of laſsiuious Rimes, is full partaker,</l>
               <l>And baudy ſongs writes with his vnchaſt pen,</l>
               <l>Which ſtinke i'th noſtrils of vertuous men:</l>
               <l>Theſe ſhew the very dreggs, and froth of wit,</l>
               <l>Which an vnprofitable, and vnfit;</l>
               <l>Theſe did at firſt the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> learne in waſte,</l>
               <l>Whoſe wits ill ſpent, giue euen as ill a taſte.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>And the <hi>Pet-Poet</hi> I muſt not forget,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Poet.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Which with good liquor doth accute his wit;</l>
               <l>And when tis got a little into's Crowne,</l>
               <l>He makes his Pen to gallup vp and downe;</l>
               <l>Writing a ſong like vnto <hi>Smug</hi> and's Daughter,</l>
               <l>Or ſome ſuch od conceite, procuring laughter.</l>
               <l>Theſe make braue ſongs, and for their greater gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</l>
               <l>Sing them in priuat, &amp; in publike places.</l>
               <l>To theſe (I ſay) as Drinke doth them imbolden,</l>
               <l>So to the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> they were firſt beholden.</l>
               <l>The Free-Schoole-Maſters,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Schoole Maſters</hi>
                  </note> which paines doe take,</l>
               <l>Good Schollers fit for <hi>Cambridge</hi> to mak,</l>
               <l>Were Infants firſt themſelues, and little Boyes,</l>
               <l>Which did delight in trifles, and in toyes,</l>
               <l>And at the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> likewiſe did begin,</l>
               <l>Before they doe ſuch good preferment win</l>
               <l>(Where youth is brought to reuerence and grace,</l>
               <l>I hold a very venerable place.)</l>
               <l>But yet ſome bad and baſely doe abuſe it,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they want diſcretion how to vſe it,</l>
               <l>Knowing no meane, nor mediocritie</l>
               <l>In their correction, but extremitie.</l>
               <l>As for example, I will here be bold</l>
               <l>To tell a tale, the like was neuer told;</l>
               <l>In the braue Hiſtorie of valliant <hi>Guy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You ſhall not reade the like for veritie:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19496:15"/>
               <l>Nor in the Mirror of Knight-hood can be found</l>
               <l>The like; for there huge lies doe loudly ſound:</l>
               <l>This is plaine truth, I pray you note it well,</l>
               <l>It is no fained fable that I tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="tale">
               <head>A Tale.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Still remember, when I was a Lad,</l>
                  <l>Long after I the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> learned had,</l>
                  <l>I paſſed ouer euery petty booke,</l>
                  <l>In which young Schollers firſt doe vſe to looke;</l>
                  <l>When as through care and coſt, I then began</l>
                  <l>To be a pretty good <hi>Gramarian.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Vnto the Free-ſchoole I was forthwith ſent</l>
                  <l>By my good Parents, with a good intent,</l>
                  <l>(That learning ſtill my mind might more adorne;</l>
                  <l>A ſweet light burden, that is eaſie borne.)</l>
                  <l>Now I begin to tell a tale of forrow</l>
                  <l>Euen of my taile: I went to <hi>Peterborrow</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To reape more learning, then before I had;</l>
                  <l>But yet I prou'd more backward, and more bad,</l>
                  <l>By reaſon that my Maſters ſtrict correction,</l>
                  <l>Turn'd quite from him my loue, and my affection,</l>
                  <l>That vnto learning then I had no mind,</l>
                  <l>To which before I greatly was inclind.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Before a <hi>Chriſtmaſſe</hi> time,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Schollers deſire libertie to play, but the euent vvas coſtly.</hi>
                     </note> we did conſpire</l>
                  <l>Againſt our Maſter, for to haue deſire</l>
                  <l>Of libertie, for double paines we tooke</l>
                  <l>All the yeare long by toyling at our booke,</l>
                  <l>VVith many a wofull ſmarting laſh beſide,</l>
                  <l>VVhich our poore buttocks patient did abide.</l>
                  <l>So with a generall and free conſent,</l>
                  <l>VVe ſhut him forth of dores incontinent;</l>
                  <l>For this did ſtrongly for our reaſon ſtand,</l>
                  <l>It was a common cuſtome through the land,</l>
                  <l>And ſince that others did attempt the ſame,</l>
                  <l>If we ſhould not doe ſo, it was a ſhame.</l>
                  <l>This we reſolu'd, and this we did performe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich made him for to ſtare, to ſtamp, &amp; ſtorme;</l>
                  <l>But yet we car'd not for his threatning words,</l>
                  <l>VVe ſtoutly ſtood with Piſtals, Pikes, &amp; Swords,</l>
                  <l>Euen like a little Armie in the field.</l>
                  <l>He could not daunt our harts, nor make vs yeeld;</l>
                  <l>Though we were boyes, yet we by this excluſion,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Manly hearts in Boyes breaſts.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shew'd in each one a manly reſolution.</l>
                  <l>Fower nights together we were priſoners kept,</l>
                  <l>The boards our beds, on which we nightly ſlept,</l>
                  <l>And for our victuals, they were neuer ſcant,</l>
                  <l>For we found friends that did relieue our want:</l>
                  <l>Yet were abundance faint and Capon-hearted,</l>
                  <l>That from their buſineſſe very baſely ſtarted.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:16"/>
                  <l>Of ſixtie proper Schollers that were found,</l>
                  <l>But ſixe of ſixtie that would ſtand their ground;</l>
                  <l>Hearing great threats, the reſt durſt neuer ſtay,</l>
                  <l>But like right Cowards ran with ſpeed away.</l>
                  <l>Had theſe been Marciall men, then Marciall law</l>
                  <l>Would ſure haue held them all in better awe,</l>
                  <l>They durſt not then haue run'd away at all,</l>
                  <l>For feare of hanging, that might after fall.</l>
                  <l>Thus were we ſix euen left vnto our ſelues,</l>
                  <l>By reaſon of thoſe baſe white-liuerd Elues:</l>
                  <l>The reſidue like fooles, and ſhallow-witted,</l>
                  <l>Went to their Maſter, and themſelues ſubmitted;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe (indeed) their bumbs began to itch,</l>
                  <l>They all went crouching for to ſaue their britch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus they eſteemed more their nether part,</l>
                  <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foule diſgrace, which woundeth ſom to t'hart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some carried tokens, bribes, and petty gifts,</l>
                  <l>To ſaue their tayles from heating by ſuch ſhifts.</l>
                  <l>But all this while we very ſtout did ſtand</l>
                  <l>Vnto the exploit that we tooke in hand;</l>
                  <l>Nor to our Maſter would we yeeld a iot,</l>
                  <l>Till a falſe pardon fondly we had got:</l>
                  <l>For he like to a falſe pernitious Wretch,</l>
                  <l>Did violate his word, and conſcience ſtretch;</l>
                  <l>He vow'd vnto the Biſhop and the Deane,</l>
                  <l>For that offence he would remit vs cleane:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>But afterwards (alas) too true we try'd,</l>
                  <l>That he like a perfidious villane ly'd;</l>
                  <l>We one by one were brought a little ſpace</l>
                  <l>Vnto the wofull execution place.</l>
                  <l>Vnto the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Bach-houſe we were led,</l>
                  <l>Where they doe vſe to make, and bake his bread<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ouer that houſe there certaine Chambers were,</l>
                  <l>Where we were brought the, with no little feare,</l>
                  <l>All intricate; and winding to and fro,</l>
                  <l>As if we in a <hi>Labyrinth</hi> did goe.</l>
                  <l>When I came there, my heart began to faile,</l>
                  <l>To ſee ſuch coſt prouided for my taile:</l>
                  <l>For he prouiſion priuily had got,</l>
                  <l>Which made my brich toſting, it was ſo hot;</l>
                  <l>There was prepared Rods a large<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elne long,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Scholler vvhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borovv.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of tuffe-red-willowes binded very ſtrong;</l>
                  <l>Pepper and ſalt he did together blend,</l>
                  <l>Full halfe a pecke he on our tayles did ſpend:</l>
                  <l>Twixt euery fower yerkes, we a handfull had</l>
                  <l>On our bare bumbs, which almoſt made vs mad.</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Tyrant</hi>-part he playd, and n'ere gaue o're,</l>
                  <l>Till he had giuen vs laſhes, fower times fower.</l>
                  <l>Thus he had ſeaſon'd well vnto his thinking,</l>
                  <l>Our wofull tay les, to keep them all from ſtinking:</l>
                  <l>And ſure (I think) that he did vnderſtand,</l>
                  <l>He Haunches had of Veniſon in hand;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:17"/>
                  <l>For I'me perſwaded, neuer man did know,</l>
                  <l>That euer Schollers tayles were powderd ſo.</l>
                  <l>It was no boote for to reſiſt at all,</l>
                  <l>Our ſtrength (alas) and number was but ſmall,</l>
                  <l>Our fellowes did our fellowſhip forſake,</l>
                  <l>And on our Maſters ſide they all did take;</l>
                  <l>We force and helpe, and weapons all did lack,</l>
                  <l>Which made our hinder-parts to goe to wrack.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we to ſhut him out did vndertake,</l>
                  <l>This Bach-houſe he a School-houſe then did make,</l>
                  <l>And ſo ſome fifty of them there he taught,</l>
                  <l>Where we to this ſam doleful place were brought,</l>
                  <l>I would himſelfe the cruell ſmart had felt,</l>
                  <l>Which by his deuilliſh ſauage hand was delt,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhould he know, that our ſo ſmall a falting,</l>
                  <l>Neuer deſerued peppering and ſalting.</l>
                  <l>For my owne griefe, to me it was beſt knowne,</l>
                  <l>I felt no bodies ſorrow but my owne;</l>
                  <l>I was in ſuch a wofull caſe, I'me ſure,</l>
                  <l>That in no certaine place I could indure:</l>
                  <l>My tayle did ſmart, I euery where was flinging,</l>
                  <l>As if a ſwarme of Bees had there been ſtinging,</l>
                  <l>I could not ſit, nor lye, nor ſtand, nor goe,</l>
                  <l>The ſalt and pepper vildly plagu'd me ſo.</l>
                  <l>Thus haue you heard a tayle of lamentation,</l>
                  <l>Euen of our tailes great griefe, and ſore vexation;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>As ſure as I the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> firſt did know,</l>
                  <l>So ſurely is he named in this <hi>Roe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This true we found to our great ſmart and paine:</l>
                  <l>Now to my <hi>Horn-booke</hi> I returne againe.</l>
                  <l>Young men and Maydens, when they firſt doe wed,</l>
                  <l>And chaſtly enter in their nuptiall bed,</l>
                  <l>Not ſuffering luſt their bodies to beguile,</l>
                  <l>Nor marriage rites, to ſpot and to defile,</l>
                  <l>According to that ſolemne vow they make,</l>
                  <l>That they each other neuer ſhall forſake</l>
                  <l>Till death depart, come pouertie, come wealth,</l>
                  <l>Come painefull ſicknes, or come perfect health:</l>
                  <l>To theſe a worthy praiſe belongs to either,</l>
                  <l>When they in Matrimony ioyne together</l>
                  <l>In a Coniunction Copplatiue moſt chaſte,</l>
                  <l>And of their neighbors Commons make no waſte.</l>
                  <l>To theſe the <hi>Horn-book</hi> proues not croſſe, but when</l>
                  <l>Women doe teach it vnto married men.</l>
                  <l>The filthy Leacher, that on drabs and queanes,</l>
                  <l>Conſumes his fleſh, his marrow, and his meanes,</l>
                  <l>Making his body to reſemble moſt</l>
                  <l>A ſinke, then temple of the holy Ghoſt;</l>
                  <l>Who cannot be contented with a wife,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet liue honeſt by a ſingle life.</l>
                  <l>The married man may be compar'd (indeed)</l>
                  <l>To a rich thiefe which ſteales, yet ſtands no need,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:18"/>
                  <l>And for ſo grieuous and ſo great abuſe,</l>
                  <l>With his beſt cunning cannot pleade excuſe</l>
                  <l>To ſaue himſelfe; Gods ſacred Maleſtie</l>
                  <l>Did preordaine a meanes and remedie</l>
                  <l>Gainſt fornication; and to hate that vice,</l>
                  <l>He honor'd Marriage firſt in Paradice;</l>
                  <l>To this intent, he did that honour giue,</l>
                  <l>That all therein, might honorably liue,</l>
                  <l>Without infringing of thoſe nuptiall bands,</l>
                  <l>By which vnited are both hearts and hands.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Bride-groome</hi> with a Ring his <hi>Bride</hi> doth wed,</l>
                  <l>In ſigne none ſhould perticipate his bed:</l>
                  <l>And as a Ring that hath no end but round,</l>
                  <l>So ſhould no ending of their loue be found<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>But they which other womens kindnes proue,</l>
                  <l>There is a breach of Wedlocks honeſt loue.</l>
                  <l>Theſe doe euen <hi>Hell</hi> for a iuſt ſtipend earne,</l>
                  <l>And ſo (indeed) the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> backwards learne.</l>
                  <l>Both married wiues, &amp; maidens here may look,</l>
                  <l>With modeſt eyes vpon my <hi>Horning-booke:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My <hi>Horne-bookes</hi> honeſty will their's affront,</l>
                  <l>If that they can vouchſafe to looke vpont;</l>
                  <l>If they be chaſte, it chaſtetie imbraceth;</l>
                  <l>It taunteth vices, and true vertue graceth:</l>
                  <l>And though the <hi>Horn-book</hi> be my books right ſtile,</l>
                  <l>Here's no laſciuious lines yet, to beguile</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>The eares of them that heare, or reade the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Though vnto ſome may harſhly ſeeme the name.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Horn-booke,</hi> if it true be vnderſtood,</l>
                  <l>Containeth nothing but is right and good.</l>
                  <l>Then wiues and Maidens, this is my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Befriend the <hi>Horn-booke,</hi> for it is your beſt.</l>
                  <l>Young hopefull Gentlemen, that doe reſort</l>
                  <l>By Art and learning to the Inns of Court,</l>
                  <l>Which doe through time and paines much vnderſtand</l>
                  <l>To grow great men, and Iudges of the land:</l>
                  <l>All theſe I reuerence with a due reſpect,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe labours turne vnto a good effect,</l>
                  <l>(I hope) their ſplendent fauours all will ſhine</l>
                  <l>Vpon my <hi>Horn-booke;</hi> though that ſome repine</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Crittick</hi>-like, doe my good meaning wreſt</l>
                  <l>To the worſt ſenſe, though I conceiue the beſt;</l>
                  <l>For (I proteſt) I thinke not an ill thought,</l>
                  <l>Though I doe itterate the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> oft;</l>
                  <l>My modeſt <hi>Muſe</hi> like to a Maid would bluſh,</l>
                  <l>If vnaduiſedly I ſhould but ruſh</l>
                  <l>Into a ſentence ſorded and vnſit,</l>
                  <l>And check my Pen, to run before my wit.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hypocro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſie.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>That man whoſe hart and tongue do not agree,</l>
                  <l>Though pure his words, his thoughts pernitious be,</l>
                  <l>The glozing ſpeeches which he doth impart,</l>
                  <l>Are characters of his deceitfull heart,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:19"/>
                  <l>His double in-ſide, out ward doth appeare</l>
                  <l>Like to the habit, that he beſt might weare,</l>
                  <l>As in a ſute of Linſie-woolſie-ſtuff,</l>
                  <l>Of lace, call'd <hi>(lack of both-ſides)</hi> for his Ruff;</l>
                  <l>His Cuffs about his wreſts iuſt of the ſame,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Ambodexter,</hi> fitteth right his name.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Religion</hi> for a cloake he putteth on</l>
                  <l>To hide his faults, when falſely he hath don,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Church he goeth moſt demure,</l>
                  <l>As if he was extreame deuout and pure;</l>
                  <l>Vnder his arme, a <hi>Bible</hi> he doth beare,</l>
                  <l>To make his luke-warme zeale more hot appeare;</l>
                  <l>When he ſpeaks faire, he then pretends moſt euill,</l>
                  <l>And Scripture falſely vſeth; like the deuill,</l>
                  <l>Who in his Diſputation went about</l>
                  <l>To tempt our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> like a Tempter ſtout.</l>
                  <l>From theſe more deuiliſh villany proceed,</l>
                  <l>Then from thoſe men that ſinfull ſeeme (indeed.)</l>
                  <l>Theſe be not <hi>Hel</hi>-black Deuils, no, they are white,</l>
                  <l>Which doe through holineſſe, in ſinne delight;</l>
                  <l>Theſe learn'd the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> to a bad intent,</l>
                  <l>Their time of learning was but vainely ſpent.</l>
                  <l>And now (my Muſe) I will not ouercharge,</l>
                  <l>I elſe could write of Pallaters at large,</l>
                  <l>Of Sumners, Baylifes and ſuch knauiſh men,</l>
                  <l>But that with them I will not foyle my pen;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19496:19"/>
                  <l>Yet in their praiſes (thus much) I can tell,</l>
                  <l>Euen in a word or two, and ſo farwell.</l>
                  <l>On the worlds ſtage, they do the deuils part play,</l>
                  <l>Which vp and downe do range to ſeek their pray,</l>
                  <l>And dailie hunt for booties where to ſpeed</l>
                  <l>On poore mens purſes moſt of all they feed,</l>
                  <l>In taking fees they ſimple men abuſe</l>
                  <l>By vild extortion, which they often vſe,</l>
                  <l>For poore men they quite ſwagger &amp; out ſweare,</l>
                  <l>Where they ſuppoſe that they can dominere;</l>
                  <l>Theſe all are Lawyers factors, for to doe</l>
                  <l>Such like imployments as they put them to.</l>
                  <l>Theſe from the <hi>Horn-books</hi> honeſt meaning ſwerue,</l>
                  <l>And in their places right like knaues doe ſerue.</l>
                  <l>Now ceaſe (my <hi>Muſe</hi>) in quiet ſilence reſt,</l>
                  <l>For of the <hi>Horn-booke</hi> thou haſt ſaid thy beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
